–They made it because... well,
as he says: it just worked out!
But it worked out that well
that they didn’t believe it at the time.
We followed on the path of metal, and we took Parabellum to a higher place.
–Parabellum? No, well, Parabellum is not an evil band
we are not evil anymore.
We are anarchist, sexuated, and crazy, and libertine
but we don’t hate that much anymore.
It was the rage and the hate,
so we set the guitars as strident as possible.
–Then we took that music and we started to send it outside,
we exchaged it.
Like: Look, listen to this! We have a metal so good
that you won’t believe it is from Colombia
–After that concert, there were some issues,
some problems in the band,
Cipriano and I ended with some hard feelings.
Then we retired and shook off from the scene.
–  BEHIND SCENES  –
–  P A R A B E L L U M  –
–  The Devil Was Born In Medellin  –
–We are in Alex Tattoo Studio in Medellin,
El Pobado neighborhood.
In 1987 we were forming Ekhymosis
I formed Masacre in 1988
Masacre is what it still is:
27 years playing metal
I think the metal scene in Medellin
starts at the beginning of the 80s
By the year…
I may say in 1984
Parabellum is formed,
then after Parabellum other
bands came up such as Mierda.
The very first time I saw them playing
it was in Manrique neighborhood
at Manrique Parking
We already had references
for a band called Parabellum
and see them playing was impressing!
It was seeing a real band with a force
and power that no other band had,
and even today I think no one
has ever played as Parabellum did.
–Yes, I live here with my auntie.
She lives on the second floor.
Here is where we rehearsed.
It was a kind of...
There it was a wall, here another wall,
there were no windows.
It was a room... a little-dark room,
we locked down us here, we turned the light off, and
we started to improvise hard songs, to play hard.
Here, to escape with the girls.
I born this way, I suffer a hip dislocation.
My spine was twisting... but not anymore,
a bioenergetic treated me
and he fixed a lot of things.
Okay, lets go!
–Are we going to?
–To Laureles
I used to live around here
This neighborhood is very cool
There is a lot of rockers, guys and girls.
(Straight forward is easier)
Here was my first time playing covers of
Plasmatics, Hypnotics, Rumble [Rumble Militia],
of various hard bands. In that garage.
Someone throw us a glass bottle
from that building
I still ignore who could be.
–Parabellum is a band that... it was not called Parabellum at first
it was called Juana La Loca
–It's Latin, it means 'Prepare for war'
It seemed a logical name for us.
'Juana La Loca' because of madness and so,
but we wanted a most concrete name for what we were going to do
that was to prepare the war against everything.
–Medellin at that time was...
just like the music: pure madness.
It was a very distorted moment.
Like if the city was being shaken all the time,
shaken by bombs, laws, problems
with values that make no sense,
with a corrupted politic
knowing the city was being directly
controlled by the Medellin Cartel,
and with rockers and metalheads
which we were a part aside
as we have nothing to do with the conflict
and we weren't interested either in the social,
politics or religion; only our music
–We were very rebels.
We were 17 - 18 years old
by 1981 we were talking about forming a band
it was when I started to study guitar
and Cipriano started to study drums/percussion too
He visited me at home
there we started to created music and rhythms,
and to record them.
Later we connected with Ramón,
further with John Jairo
–What's up?
–What's up? How are you doing?
–How are you doing?
–I'm fine!
–What's the pet's name?
–Eh, Minea
In 1985 specifically was when I formed the band
with the capability to play metal
and with the instruments.
In 1985 I started with 'El Gato'
and Federico López
to assemble some music.
Later in 1987 we offer our
first concert, in September
In 1988 we entered to a studio
at Raimond Records
to recording our first LP
which by chance ended being
the first metal LP from Colombia
Well...
I remember once we were
in downtown
and suddenly appeared
a very strange thing
with long hair almost until it knees
you couldn't guess if that was
walking forward or backward
We start talking
I smoked a lot of weed at that time,
but this man only drinks milk and cake,
now is the opposite.
–Totally straight edge!
–Anyway... Everything was cool,
and Parabellum was tremendous impressive!
Since I heard Parabellum,
and that's why I recognized him,
because I already knew Parabellum.
I didn't attend the two gigs
at Parqueadero Manrique
but I did at Battle Of The Bands...
A very crazy thing!
A tremendous thing!
– BATTLE OF THE BANDS 1985 –
That concert promised that
the most voted band by the public
will be rewarded with recording a disc.
So the people started to communicate:
"Hey, Parabellum will play!"
"Mierda will play!"
"Danger will play!"
I'm talking about the people
that lived in the slums
what we call lower 'estrato'
(Lower social class)
There was another higher 'estrato'
people from El Poblado, Envigado,
that were supporting bands as Kraken, Spol, etc.
that wanted to be rockstars,
become famous, etc.
Once Parabellum started to play
that event became a shit!
A big shit!
The people startet to show...
As I haven't been to a Parabellum concert before,
it was brutal to me!
It was a bestial sound!
No one knew such a sound before.
Nowhere.
After Parabellum it was Kraken's turn
but Kraken couldn't even
make it to the stage!
Because when people knew
that the next band was Kraken,
the people became really angry
and started to throw rocks,
and anything they found.
The people from the stands took the signs
that were placed on the seats,
they were throwing things
down to the arena,
the people from the arena were
throwing things up to the stands...
They almost throw down
the scaffolding
in the middle of the plaza Macarena,
down on the ground...
It was a very violent thing!
Right there was evident
the division between
the commercial sound and
the 'underground' sound
in the Medellin scene
As Kraken didn't play,
people thought that
the disc recording prize
was going to be to Parabellum,
as everyone was in
favor of Parabellum,
but six months later,
it was released 'Kraken' disc
–Hmm
Where is that building is
where first was the church
Once we all got arrested after
a concert we offered there
As I understand,
the priest, after renting us
the church for $8.000 pesos
called the police saying
the ELN guerrilla took over the place,
so the police came
shooting into the air
and kicking us all out of here.
The priest got scared when he saw
that many 'crazy' people,
He was confused.
Those were really hard times.
We ended up arrested
almost always.
–Right.
There was no respect
for the people or anything.
–Yes. We all were bullied us a lot.
You couldn't walk freely
in some places because
you risk someone cuts your hair,
or throw glue into your head
to force you to cut it,
or things like that, etc.
It was a problem.
Very repressive actions
from the authorities
or "authorities" in quotation marks,
and the Christianism - Catholicism
very dogmatic here,
totally conservative;
almost fascist
that restricted a lot of opportunities
for young people at that time,
when we were young, right?
That may explain the social reaction
and the aggressivity,
the violence toward us.
–Let's go to 6 p.m. Mass,
6 p.m. Mass!
We'll be right back!
–We want a 'tasty' cookie
[church wafer]
–(What a beautiful 'mammies')
(hello, pretties!)
BM
–Who makes the contacts with foreign companies?
–I am the one in contact
with the foreign market
mainly with people
from Europe,
Alex makes the contact with
people from South America
–Mauricio "Bull Metal" was a guy
that made contacts
with people in Europe
and the United States.
He was the first who wrote
to the Norwegians,
to Euronymous of Mayhem.
In letters they sent letters to us,
they said they had metal
but a rollerskaters metal,
a jumping metal.
A metal more like Anthrax or Metalica,
not a raw metal as you guys have there
(in Colombia)
–To say that Scandinavian metal
came from Parabellum
is a thesis that has circulated
in the scene, right?
–Norwegian metal is almost...
is almost born with Mayhem
Venom is from 1979
They released their major album
in 1982:
Black Metal by Venom
Parabellum is from 1984
Mayhem is from 1984 - 1985
They took that raw and abrupt sound,
and start to associate it with religion.
They start to enter into the obscure.
They start to use makeup,
to radicalize themselves more,
to arson on churches,
a murder of a homosexual,
to attack prostitutes...
Basically against everything they think
is not the way they think it should be.
–The hardest thing we had to exchange
with Mayhem was Parabellum
so we sent Parabellum,
then they said it was impressive
a metal band like Parabellum
existed in Colombia
–TO FEED WORMS, IT'S YOUR EXISTENCE–
–TO BREAK BARRIERS, YOU ARE CONSCIOUS–
–DOORS, WINDOWS, WALLS, AND FENCES–
–SMOKE ON THE GROUND, LAWS AND RULES–
–SCREAMING AND LAUGHING ON YOUR BRAIN–
–[UNINTELLIGIBLE], OH!, DIRTY WORLD–
–The thing with the sound,
it was because of the lack of
knowledge and technique we had
–Also...
–As I said...
–Also the tools..
–Exactly, the tools we had were very...
very...
–Precarious
–Precarious. Very scarce,
for example, the distortions
were made by friends
who half knew about...
–(Electronics)
–Electronics,
so they make us a distortion
that sounded barely similar,
that's why it sounded
that strident.
–HOMICIDAL SCIENCE, IT'S JUST APPEARANCE–
–FORMING DISORDER, PLANTING DEMENTIA–
–CREATING CHILDREN, IN TEST TUBES–
–DAMN WITCH, DON'T INTERMIT–
The music was half-chromatic
and half-melodic
so when combined it sounded hard,
and because of the dark lyrics too;
and our method had that intention,
making things with deep feelings
and rigorous work.
–It wasn't only Parabellum,
later we send to them
Reencarnación,
Eh... Masacre too;
they had a place
that was like...
like a cave,
where they met to drink
and listen to music.
The walls were scratched
with bands logos
and there was Parabellum,
Reencarnación, Masacre...
They said there was a special place,
a cult, for Colombian metal.
–I think it's the sort of thing
that happens by chance,
things arrive there, things arrive here;
they mix.
Someone gets interested
in something.
The same way as I was
interested in Parabellum,
Maybe Mayhem was
in Reencarnación.
–Oh, no. My family was very relaxed,
they never felt uncomfortable about this.
They got a little bit scared
when we released Sacrilegio...
because of the cover...
because we 'improve' the Virgin.
People was scared of that!
We just wanted to spit on everything,
so... we will release it this way, you like it or not!
While recording the first Sacrilegio album
we had a lot of problems
I think God didn't want us to record that disc
because we were very evil
but we made it anyway with the Devil's help.
During the first record sessions,
we had several issues.
When they placed the vinyl to make the first copies,
the main equipment got burned literally,
they had electricity cuts, suddenly equipment malfunction,
and even the studio was frightening;
so they blamed us for all that
because we were a very dark band,
And they banned us! After releasing Sacrilegio
they never allowed us to record there anymore.
(DISCOS FUENTES LOGO)
In 1985 was the concert at La Macarena,
after La Macarena concert we had another concert
with Mierda, at Parqueadero Manrique.
After that concert, there were some issues,
some problems in the band,
also with Mierda members too.
Cipriano and I ended with some hard feelings
because of that situation with them.
Then we retired and shook off the scene...
–Its raw, dark, and strident sound
called as 'Ultra Metal', made Parabellum
a cult band for the underground metal.–
In 1987 we recorded Sacrilegio,
and in 1988, Mutación Por Radiación;
but the band was already disintegrated.
I insisted on recording the songs
for they don't disappear into the air.
Cipriano didn't want anything anymore,
the other members were gone.
I was the only one who wanted
to left proof of what we have done,
and let it spread.
–In 1998, guitar, John Jairo Martínez
was murdered in a fight.–
–In 1986, Ramón Restrepo, vocals,
formed Blasfemia, a Medellin's black metal
cult band that is still performing.–
–I think the scene ended for them
because punk and hardcore arrived,
and...
I think, maybe that led
each of them to other things.
Maybe they realized that
writing always about 'Satan' or
against religion was not longer the way,
instead move towards social critic.
–After leaving the band, Tomás Cipriano, Parabellum lyrics and drums,
made a cameo in Rodrigo D. No Futuro movie,
where 'La Bruja' also participated in the sound.–
–After the movie premiere, and form punk bands
as HP.HC and Rebelión, Cipriano left the scene.–
–He is currently living in the outskirts of Medellin
and refused to declare anything for this documentary–
–Carlos Mario is someone who made big things
for the music, for the metal of the world.
What Parabellum did...
they set a bar very high,
I think absolutely no one can erase that,
no one can forget that,
no one can deny that.
Nowadays they could be one of
the biggest bands in the world.
If they were still performing,
I'm sure they would be as important
as Mayhem, Bathory, or Venom.
–(Thank you! So cool. Bye!)–
–We are with Víctor Raúl, 'Piolín'.
(Well, I don't know why the 'Tweety Bird' nickname,
but we made a lot of fun of it.)
People said that he liked a lot the 'birds' (dicks),
but I can't confirm!
–Hahaha
(No? I'm so sorry, dude.)
–It was at first grade in primary school,
Principal called me that once.
–Ah, alright
We made a lot of fun for that anyway.